A Finding Aid to the Lloyd Goodrich Papers, 1884-1987, bulk 1927-1987 in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Lloyd Goodrich papers
1884-1987
bulk 1927-1987
Archives of American Art
Goodrich, Lloyd, 1897-1987
AAA.goodlloy
Archival Resource Key
35.7 Linear feet
The papers of art historian, writer, and museum administrator Lloyd Goodrich measure 35.7 linear feet and date from 1884 to 1987 with the bulk of the material dating from 1927 to 1987. Materials include biographical material, extensive correspondence, writings and research files, organization and committee files, exhibition files, printed material, a scrapbook, and photographic material. The collection is particularly rich in research files on Winslow Homer, Thomas Eakins, Albert Pinkham Ryder, and Reginald Marsh, as well as correspondence with additional notable artists and art figures.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1946-1984 (Boxes 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1920-1987 (Boxes 1-3; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Research Files, 1884-1987 (Boxes 3-17, 38; 14.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Organization and Committee files, 1933-1982 (Boxes 17-31, 37; 14.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Exhibition Files, 1944-1986 (Boxes 31-32; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, circa 1920s-1979 (Boxes 32-33; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Scrapbook, 1952-1959 (Box 33; 2 folders)
Series 8: Photographic Materials, circa 1910-1987 (Boxes 33-37; 3.1 linear feet)
Biographical / Historical
Lloyd Goodrich (1897-1987) was a prominent and influential art historian, writer, and director of the Whitney Museum of Art in New York City, New York, from 1958-1968.
Lloyd Goodrich was born in Nutley, New Jersey in 1897. He studied under Kenneth Hayes Miller at the Art Students League from 1913-1915 and also took courses at the National Academy of Design. Rather than pursue a career as an artist, however, he decided that his real talent was writing about art. He began his long and prolific writing career in 1923-24 and married Edith Havens in 1924. Inspired by the work and writings of European art scholars and a desire to address the need for a body of scholarship on American Art, Goodrich began to research and write about American artists Kenneth Hayes Miller, Winslow Homer, and Thomas Eakins.
Goodrich's first article on Winslow Homer was published in 1924 by The Arts, a magazine financed by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney and edited by Forbes Watson, who soon hired Goodrich as associate editor. By 1929, Goodrich was also working as assistant art critic for the New York Times while continuing work at The Arts as contributing editor. One year later, The Arts commissioned Goodrich to write a book on Kenneth Hayes Miller. And, around the same time Goodrich became interested in Thomas Eakins, and with the encouragement and financial support from his boyhood friend, artist Reginald Marsh, he began work on a monograph about Eakins.
In 1930, Goodrich joined the staff of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney's new American art museum in New York City, the Whitney Museum of American Art. The museum provided him with the funds he needed to research and complete his book on Thomas Eakins, which he achieved in 1933. In 1935, he became curator of the museum, and associate director in 1948. He served as director from 1958-1968. The bequest of the Edward Hopper collection to the Whitney was the result of Goodrich's reputation as a scholar of Edward Hopper. After retiring, Goodrich continued his association with the Whitney as advisory director and director emeritus.
Goodrich was instrumental in starting the American Art Research Council in 1942, a group of museums devoted to collecting scholarly records about American art. He sat on the advisory panels for the New York State Council on the Arts and the Fine Arts Advisory Committee to the White House. In 1933, he was in charge of the New York regional office of the Public Works of Art Project. He also served as chairman of the National Council on the Arts and Government from 1948 to 1954 and was a major force in the creation of the National Endowment for the Arts and Humanities. He was a member of the Artists Equity Association, Artist Tenants Association, and numerous other arts organizations and a strong advocate for the promotion and support of American art and artists.
Throughout his long and distinguished career as a writer and museum administrator, Lloyd Goodrich worked to build a body of scholarship related to the history of American art and artists. He published several important monographs, including works on Thomas Eakins, Edward Hopper, Albert Pinkham Ryder, Winslow Homer, and Reginald Marsh, and organized major exhibitions about these and many other artists during his 57-year association with the Whitney Museum of American Art. At the time of his death, Goodrich was considered a preeminent figure in the American art world, and one of the foremost authorities on Eakins, Ryder, and Homer, artists on which he kept extensive research files throughout his life.
Lloyd Goodrich died March 27, 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Lloyd Goodrich papers were given to the Archives of American Art in several different acquisitions. Lloyd Goodrich first donated material in 1983. David Goodrich, Lloyd Goodrich's son, gave more material between 1988 and 2007 while additional papers were lent for microfilming by William I. Homer in 1990. Finally, the Whitney Museum of American Art donated papers in 1996, and Polly Thistlethwaite gave further material in 2015.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Lloyd Goodrich, 1962-1963 by Harlan Phillips for the Archives of American Art.
Additional Lloyd Goodrich papers are located at the Whitney Museum of American Art Archives, and the Philadelphia Museum of Art Archives.
Scope and Contents
The papers of art historian, writer, and museum administrator Lloyd Goodrich measure 35.7 linear feet and date from 1884 to 1987 with the bulk of the material dating from 1927 to 1987. Materials include biographical material, extensive correspondence, writings and research files, organization and committee files, exhibition files, printed material, a scrapbook, and photographic material. The collection is particularly rich in research files on Winslow Homer, Thomas Eakins, Albert Pinkham Ryder, and Reginald Marsh, as well as correspondence with additional notable artists and art figures.
Scattered biographical materials include biographical sketches, an interview transcript, personal business records, documents relating to Goodrich's service on art juries, and awards and honors.
Correspondence is with friends, family, artists, museums, collectors, galleries, and arts organizations. Correspondents include The Arts Magazine, Whitney Museum of Art, Olin Dows, Philip Evergood, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Reginald Marsh, Kenneth Hayes Miller, Elias Newman, Daniel Catton Rich, and Raphael Soyer among many others. Research related correspondence arranged here concerns work on a catalogue raisonné of Winslow Homer. This material was originally arranged in the correspondence files by Goodrich prior to the later donation that included additional research files on Homer found in Series 3. There are also condolence letters from notable figures in American art.
Writings and research files include major writings, such as books and articles, and book reviews, essays, exhibition text, catalog entries, and lectures. In addition to the writings, Goodrich's research files for the writings are arranged here and include research, notes, correspondence, photographs, illustrations, printed materials, and bibliographies. There are also book agreements. There are extensive files for Goodrich's books on Winslow Homer (see also correspondence in Series 2) and Reginald Marsh; articles, catalog entries, and other writings on Winslow Homer, Albert Pinkham Ryder, Kuniyoshi, Reginald Marsh, and American art in general; lectures and talks; research files on other artists, and notes and notebooks.
Organization and committee files document Goodrich's service on boards, commissions, committees, organizations, and associations, such as the American Federation of Arts, the Association of Art Museum Directors, the Carnegie Study in American Art, the National Council on the Arts and Government, American Art Research Council, Artists Equity Association, Artist Tenants Association, the selection committee of the American National Exhibition (1959), and others are found within organization and committee files. Agendas, correspondence, meeting minutes, and printed material are found within the files.
Exhibition files are found only for several Winslow Homer shows. Printed materials include clippings, publicity materials, and printed copies of his writings. Photographic material includes scattered photographs of Goodrich and others, and extensive negatives of works of art, likely by Homer. Also found are x-rays of paintings by Ralph Blakelock.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming (reel 4468) including a photocopy of the manuscript "Albert Pinkham Ryder: The Man and His Art," Goodrich's contribution to the book "Albert Pinkham Ryder: Painter of Dreams" co-authored with William I. Homer. Loaned materials were returned to the lender and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Existence and Location of Copies
Material lent for microfilming is available on 35mm microfilm reel 4468 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Art historians -- New York (State) -- New York; Art -- Collectors and collecting -- New York (State) -- New York; Arts administrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Art, American; Museum curators -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Museum directors -- New York (State) -- New York; Museum administrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Transcripts; Interviews; Scrapbooks; Art museums -- New York (State); Evergood, Philip, 1901-1973; Eakins, Thomas, 1844-1916; Homer, Winslow, 1836-1910; Dows, Olin, 1904-1981; Marsh, Reginald, 1898-1954; Kuniyoshi, Yasuo, 1889-1953; American Federation of Arts; Miller, Kenneth Hayes, 1876-1952; American Art Research Council; Newman, Elias, 1903-; Ryder, Albert Pinkham, 1847-1917; Rich, Daniel Catton, 1904-1976; National Council on the Arts and Government; Whitney Museum of American Art; Artists Equity Association; Association of Art Museum Directors; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987; Artist Tenants Association (New York, N.Y.)
- Biographical Materials, 1946-1984; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Found are biographical sketches, a copy of Goodrich's birth certificate, a transcript of an interview with Goodrich, awards and honors, documents relating to Goodrich's service as an art juror, and scattered personal business records, including a letter to Juliana Force regarding salary negotiations.
  - Art Juror Service, 1954-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Awards and Honors Files, 1946-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-10)
  - Biographical Sketches, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Birth Certificate (Copy), circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Interview Transcript, with Lloyd Goodrich by Ms. Margaret Debrot, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Personal Business Records, 1946-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1920-1987; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.8 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Arrangement
  Correspondence regarding research on Winslow Homer was donated at a later date and not integrated into the Homer research files donated earlier. The bulk of Goodrich's files, including correspondence, regarding his work on Winslow Homer is found in Series 3.
  Correspondence is with museums, galleries, friends, colleagues, arts organizations, and his wife Edith Havens Goodrich. Correspondents include W. G. Brownwell, Bryson Burroughs, Olin Dows, Philip Evergood, John Fletcher, George Fuller, Rosalie Warner James, Augusta Kelley, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Reginald and Betty Marsh, Kenneth Hayes Miller, Cyril Nast, Elias Newman, Daniel Catton Rich, Raphael Soyer, Mrs. Silvia S. Warner, and Faith Weston. Also found is a file of letters concerning RIchard Yarde. There is also a group of correspondence concerning Goodrich's work on a catalogue raisonné of Winslow Homer.
  Most of the correspondence between Goodrich, Kuniyoshi, and Marsh was sent between 1925 and 1926 when the Marshes and Kuniyoshi and his first wife, Katherine Schmidt, were traveling in Europe over the course of the year. Marsh writes of the art and architecture of Europe and reports on the doings of friends he runs across, such as Kuniyoshi, Schmidt, and Guy Pène du Bois. Many of the travel letters are illustrated.
  Also found in this series are condolence letters to David Goodrich upon his father's death in 1987 from John I.H. Baur, Flora Biddle, Dean Fausett, Lawrence Fleischman, Karl and Ilse Schrag, Roy Neuberger, Helen Farr Sloan, Raphael Soyer, Ira Spanierman, Jane Turano, Betty Burroughs Woodhouse, Virginia Zabriskie, and others.
  Researchers should note that additional correspondence is found among the writings and research files in Series 3 and the organizational and committee files in Series 4.
  - Personal, 1924-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15-19)
  - The Arts Magazine, 1929-1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1950-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Yarde, Richard, 1983-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Condolence Letters, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General, 1920-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24-32)
  - General, 1920-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Research Correspondence, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - General, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - General, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - General, 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
    - General, 1960-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10-16)
    - General, 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
    - General, 1980-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Research Correspondence, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    - General, 1980-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Calo, Mary Ann, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cooper, Helen, 1976-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Gerdts, William, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Gould, Jean; Hannaway, Patti, 1962-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Tatham, David, 1965-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - Weinberg, Barbara, 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Writings and Research Files, 1884-1987; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 14.5 Linear feet Box 3-17, 38
  Writings and research files document Goodrich's research and writing projects and include files relating to his published books on Winslow Homer and Reginald Marsh, as well as articles, lectures, talks, drafts of lectures and talks, book reviews, encyclopedia entries, exhibition catalog essays, and other publications. Many of the writing files include scattered research notes. Also found are research and reference files arranged by topic or name, notebooks, lists, annotated printed materials, and files titled "ideas".
  This series is arranged as 5 subseries.
  Missing Title
  3.1: Books, 1884-1990s
  3.2: For Publication, 1936-1986
  3.3: Lectures and Speeches, 1933-1983
  3.4: Research and Reference Files, circa 1917-1986
  3.5: General, 1930-1972
  - Books, 1884-1990s; 3.1; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
    Found are materials relating to Goodrich's published works Winslow Homer and Reginald Marsh, including bibliographies, correspondence, drafts, illustrations, photographs, printed material, and research material.
    - Winslow Homer, Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
      - Drafts, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12-22)
    - Winslow Homer, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, Harry S. Abrams, 1969-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, Mrs. William A. Preston, 1937-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Research, Auctions, 1940s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
      - Research, Biography, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Research, Collectors, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Research, Cooper-Hewitt, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Research, Dealers, 1931-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8-12)
      - Research, Museums, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Research, New England, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Research, Prout's Neck, 1884-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Research, Technical, 1968-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Lists of Contacts, circa 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Illustrations, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
      - Information Sheets for Works of Art, circa 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Notes, on Catalog Style, 1937-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Xeroxes of Works of Art and Exhibition Material, 1940s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
      - Winslow Homer Graphics, 1938-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24-28)
      - Printed Material, circa 1900-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 29-31)
    - Winslow Homer, Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
      - Printed Material, circa 1900-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
        Oversized material housed in OV 38
      - Bibliography, 1911-1986, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11-19)
      - Bibliography, Books, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Winslow Homer, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
      - Bibliography, Museum Bulletins, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Bibliography, Newspapers, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
      - Bibliography, Periodicals, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4-9)
      - Photographs of Works of Art, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10-24)
    - Winslow Homer, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
      - Photographs of Works of Art, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1-10)
    - Reginald Marsh, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 1942-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11-14)
      - Correspondnece, Frederick Dana Marsh, 1931-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Research and Reference, 1936-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 16-21)
      - General, 1951-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - Illustrations, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 24-25)
    - Reginald Marsh, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
      - Illustrations, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Layout, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Notes, 1954-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Clippings, 1933-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Photographs, 1956-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 5-16)
      - Duplicates, 1935-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
    - Oversized Printed Material, from Box 5, Folder 10, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 38)
  - For Publication, 1936-1986; 3.2; Archival Resource Key
    Many of the original folder titles have been kept although they may have been standardized. Materials are arranged in rough chronological order by the earliest dated material within a folder.
    This subseries includes articles, book reviews, introductions to books by others, encyclopedia entries, exhibition catalog texts, and other works intended for publication by Goodrich.
    - on Copley, The North American Review, 1936-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - "Renior," Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - "A Century of American Landscape Painting," North American Review, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Foreword, Winslow Homer: A Brief Life and Critical Estimate of His Works," by John W. Beatty, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Review, American Painting, by Virgil Barker, 1940-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 23-24)
    - Catalog, Watercolor Exhibition (1945), Walker Art Center, 1942-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Reviews, Various, 1942-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - The Artists' America, 1943-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Catalog, American Watercolor and Winslow Homer Exhibition, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - "Criticism and Scholarship," Magazine of Art, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Review, Washington Allston, by Edgar Preston Richardson, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "What is American in American Art?" for Art in America, 1948-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
    - "The State of American Art," Magazine of Art, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "Ralph Earl," Magazine of Art, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Preface, Milestones of American Painting in Our Century, by Frederick S. Wight, circa 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "Realism and Romanticism in Homer, Eakins, and Ryder," Art Quarterly, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "Harnett and Peto: A Note on Style," The Art Bulletin, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Review, Art and Life in America, by Oliver Larkin, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Catalog, Art Students League 75th Anniversary Exhibition (1951), Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - "The Painting of American History," American Quarterly, 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Edits, Kenneth Hayes Miller, by Lincoln Rothschild, 1952-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 14-17)
    - Editorial on the National Sculpture Society, Art Digest, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 18-19)
    - Review, Socialism and American Life, by Egbert, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Exhibition Review, Landmarks in American Art, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Edits, Recollections of Winslow Homer: An Intimate Friendship, by John W. Beatty, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Reply to Open Letter, Arts Digest, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - "The Whitney's Battle for U.S. Art," Art News, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - "Reginald Marsh," American Artist, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - "Winslow Homer," Perspectives, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Catalog, Kuniyoshi Exhibition, University of Florida, 1955-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - on Andrew Wyeth Portfolio, Art in America, 1955-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - on Federal Advisory Commission on the Arts, College Art Journal, 1955-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Letter to the Editor, College Art Journal, 1955-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 30)